<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
         xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
  <control>
    <recordId>Bouverie-Street</recordId>
    <maintenanceStatus>new</maintenanceStatus>
    <maintenanceAgency>
      <agencyCode>AU-EMEL</agencyCode>
      <agencyName>eMelbourne - The Encyclopedia of Melbourne Online</agencyName>
      <descriptiveNote><p></p></descriptiveNote>
    </maintenanceAgency>
    <languageDeclaration>
      <language languageCode="eng">English</language>
      <script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
    </languageDeclaration>
    <conventionDeclaration>
      <abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
      <citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
    </conventionDeclaration>
    <localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
      <term>Entry</term>
    </localControl>
    <maintenanceHistory>
      <maintenanceEvent>
        <eventType>created</eventType>
        <eventDateTime standardDateTime="2026-07-21">2026-07-21</eventDateTime>
        <agentType>human</agentType>
        <agent>Andy May</agent>
        <eventDescription>Public contribution via website submission</eventDescription>
      </maintenanceEvent>
    </maintenanceHistory>
  </control>
  <cpfDescription>
    <identity>
      <entityId>Bouverie-Street</entityId>
      <entityType>concept</entityType>
      <nameEntry>
        <part>Bouverie Street</part>
        <authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
      </nameEntry>
    </identity>
    <description>
      <places></places>
      <biogHist>
        <abstract>Bouverie Street runs from Grattan Street in the north to Victoria Street in the south. It was likely named after a street in London. 

A number of Melbourne streets were renumbered in the late 1880s and it seems that Bouverie Street may have been one of them. A funeral notice in the Age [can I italicise this]  21 March 1889, p. 8 [can I link to the Trove item? http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article196995283] notes that the funeral of James McMahon will leave his late residence, 57 old number, 85 new, Bouverie Street, Carlton.

Andrew May&apos;s book &quot;Melbourne Street Life&quot; notes the following: &quot;An unsuccessful application was made to change the name of Carlton’s Bouverie Street in order to attract a better class of tenants, the street having ‘lost caste’ in the view of its property owners because of the occupation by undesirable classes&quot;. My notes suggest that there were 35 signatories to the petition, which was not granted. The complaints of the petitioners was that &quot;The street in the past had many Tenements, occupied by very Undesirable persons … Consequently the street lost caste, and the values have fallen from a rental and selling point of view … If the name were altered, a better class of tenants would be induced to live there, being so close to the University and city. It should be a splendid residential street and the increased value of the properties would greatly benefit the city revenue&quot;. 

The archival reference for this is VPRS 3181/870, 1901 File 715. The original should be checked and digitised.</abstract>
      </biogHist>
    </description>
    <relations>
      <resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
        <relationEntry localType="published">'Bouverie Street', in &lt;span style="font-style:italic"&gt;eMelbourne - The Encyclopedia of Melbourne Online&lt;/span&gt;, School of Historical Studies, Department of History, The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>
        <objectXMLWrap>
          <bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
            <title render="italic">Bouverie Street</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>School of Historical Studies&lt;br /&gt; Department of History, The University of Melbourne</publisher>
            </imprint>
            <bibseries>
              <title render="italic">eMelbourne - The Encyclopedia of Melbourne Online</title>
            </bibseries>
            <extptr linktype="simple" href="Bouverie-Street.xml"></extptr>
          </bibref>
        </objectXMLWrap>
      </resourceRelation>
    </relations>
  </cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>